Jester Hairston Collection MS040
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Jester Hairston Collection
1920 -- 1970
1910 -- 1998
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Hairston, Jester Joseph
MS040
45.85 Linear Feet
10 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series: Sound recordings related to Jester Hairston; Sound recordings unrelated to Jester Hairston; and Jester Hairston subject files and musical scores. Each series is arranged by record size, first 12-inch records and then 10-inch records, and organized alphabetically within each subsection. The 12-inch records in series 2 are roughly alphabetized. Foreign language records are located at the end of series 1 and 2.
Custodial History
The records in this collection were part of a larger donation that Jester Hairston had wanted to deposit at Tufts University in the 1990s. For various reasons only the records were eventually accepted as donation. These were likely his personal record collection, including records recorded by him, purchased by him, given to him, or sent to him for professional review.
The collection documentation folder indicates that collection materials arrived at Tufts sometime between March-July 1993. Rose Oliveira, 2016-04-22
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of phonograph records, interviews, correspondence, clippings, press releases, speeches, musical scores, photographs, and student records. The bulk of the collection consists of approximately 800 record albums on which Hairston either appeared, or which he collected. Genres represented include jazz, blues, choral, spoken word, contemporary Christian, gospel, orchestral, folk, classical, and world music, dating from 1910-1990. Hairston was well-known for his compositions of 'Negro' spirituals, many of which are represented in the collection. The content of some unlabeled recordings in this collection are unknown because the material is not accessible using conventional record playing equipment. Also included are biographical materials on Hairston and subject files and musical scores by other composers.
Approximately one third of the records in this collection are directly related to Hairston; he either appears as conductor, director, performer, composer or artist on the albums. Some of the records appear to be unique recordings of Hairston, possibly made during rehearsals and never formally produced. A large portion of these records document Hairston's role as guest conductor at high school and university choirs throughout the United States from the 1960s-1980s, as well as his role as an international ambassador of music. Also included are records inscribed to Hairston or bearing other markings that relate to him. Foreign language records include those in Spanish, Russian, Danish, German, French, Greek, Swedish, Finnish, and Portuguese. The rest of the collection is comprised of records that were part of Hairston's personal collection, but in whose he recording he played no role. This section includes many commercially available records from the 1970s and 1980s, as well as rare 78rpm recordings from 1910-1930. The content of some unlabeled recordings in this collection are unknown because the material is not accessible using conventional record playing equipment.
The Hairston subject files and musical scores compose the smallest part of the collection. It contains a small amount of biographical information included press releases, interviews, speeches and student records. Also included, are subject files and musical scores by other composers and collaborators with Hairston. This includes Salli Terri (1922-1996), a popular 1960s singer, arranger, recording artist, and composer. She was also a professor of music and director of a woman's choir at UCLA and collaborated on several projects with Hairston.
Parts of this collection may be restricted due to condition.
Biographical / Historical
Jester Hairston (1901-2000) worked as composer, arranger, singer, conductor, and actor. He is known primarily as one of a small number of African American composers whose work transformed African-American spirituals into an accepted genre of choral music.
Hairston was born July 1, 1901 in Bellows Creek, North Carolina, near the plantation where his grandparents had been enslaved. Not long after his birth, the Hairston family moved to a steel mill town near Pittsburgh by the name of Homestead. Of this town, Hairston said, "There's nothing to do there but work in steel mills. That's the reason I got out of there as quickly as I could." Hairston attended University of Massachusetts in Amherst on a two year church scholarship, but was unable to continue for lack of money. He began working and met Northampton schoolteacher, Laura Anna Kidder. She was so impressed with his musical talent that she was willing to pay for his education with her savings. He subsequently repaid her for her loan. Hairston had applied to Tufts University, which was know for its music department, and was turned down. After his rejection, Hairston ran into a friend in New York, who was also African-American and who had been admitted to Tufts for his athletic skills. This student advised Hairston to write a letter to the music department and to "lay it on thick!" Hairston followed his advice and auditioned for Leo R. Lewis, the head of the music department on Lewis' front porch and was subsequently admitted. Hairston graduated from Tufts in 1929 and went on to study music theory at Julliard for two years.
After leaving Julliard, Hairston became the assistant director of the Hall Johnson Choir in New York and it was there that he developed his interest in African-American spirituals. For a short time he organized the African American 'The Jester Hairston Singers,' one of whose members was Margaret Isabel Swanigan who became his wife in 1939. In 1934/35 WPA hired him as assistant director of one of the largest music schools in New York City for African American children and adults. In 1935, the Hall Johnson Choir went to California to perform in the film, "Green Pastures." The next year Hairston made his break as a composer in Hollywood with the film "Lost Horizons" and also performed with Shirley Temple and her choir. The Hall Johnson choir also performed with Irvin Cobb on the Paducah plantation radio program for the Oldsmobile people for 26 weeks which was sponsored by GM and canceled eventually due to GM's prolonged difficulties with the famous sit down strikes in Michigan which invigorated the UAW. In 1937, the Hall Johnson choir gave a private concert for Stravinsky at Paramount studio after which Stravinsky planned to compose a group of choral works for the Hall Johnson Choir, mentioned in a contemporary letter by Hairston. Throughout the 1940s, he arranged choral music in over 40 films such as "Dual in the Sun," "Friendly Persuasion," and "Red River." He became one of Hollywood's most respected choral directors during this time period. When filmmakers stopped using large choral ensembles, Hairston performed as a character actor (often uncredited) in television and films, including "The Alamo," "Carmen Jones: "Tarzan," "To Kill a Mockingbird," "So This is Love," "Tanganyika" (an African movie), "Gypsy Colt," "Tarzan's Secret Jungle," St. Louis Blues and "In the Heat of the Night," "Lady Sings the Blues," "I'm Gonna Git You Sucka," "The Bingo Long Traveling All, Stars and Motor Kings," "Tender Killing Care," and "Being John Malkovich". Hairston also portrayed Henry Van Porter and Leroy Smith in the controversial radio and television show "Amos 'n Andy." By 1951, he had also performed as Johnny in the Beulah Show and at Humphrey Bogart's new radio show, Bold Venture, as a Cuban singer. The US government sent him and an integrated choir on a good will tour to Asia in the 1950s.
Most importantly, Hairston was a prolific composer. He is most famous for "Amen," a spiritual so "authentic" many did not realize Hairston had composed it. The song was made famous through the film "Lilies of the Field;" Hairston performed the song, dubbing for lead actor, Sidney Poitier. In addition to composing film scores, Hairston composed or arranged more than 300 choral spirituals, including popular compositions such as "Elijah" and "Mary's Little Boy Child." Hairston, an expert in the history of African-American folk music and Negro spirituals, became one of the foremost interpreters, arrangers, and composers of this music, once stating ''I decided that I wanted to make my mark in folk songs because my grandparents were slaves […] I wanted to keep that music alive.''
Numerous music records include Jester Hairston as singer, composer, or conductor such as "Calypso Christmas" on Victor with the voices of Walter Shumann, "Christmas in the air" and "Great Getting' up mornin," "The Afro-American slave song: its African roots and American development" (Jester Hairston Metropolitan Choir), "A profile of Negro life in song," "Mary's boy child" (Venezuela), "Tarzan and the Mermaid" (Jester Hairston Choir) among many others.
Throughout the 1970s and 80s, Hairston was honored for his work across the US and he was frequently invited as guest conductor at high schools, colleges and church choirs. He also made several State Department sponsored goodwill tours to Africa, Asia, Europe and South America, once stating, "I will bring more love to China through American Negro folk songs than anything Kissinger can write." Throughout his lifetime, Hairston broke down many racial barriers in the United States. He was, for instance, the first African-American to be invited to conduct in the Mormon Tabernacle choir. Occasionally criticized for taking film and television roles that stereotyped African-Americans, Hairston said, "We had a hard time fighting for dignity. We had no power. We had to take it, and because we took it, the young people today have opportunities."
Late in his life, Hairston was active in organizing national reunions of the Hairston family, which traces its lineage to the Antebellum American South and sponsored reunions for both black and white descendents. The family, and Jester Hairston in particular, was the subject of Henry Wiencek's 1999 book ''The Hairstons: An American Family in Black and White.'' Wiencek wrote of Hairston, ''He never let go of his anger over slavery, but he also forgave. Still, he insisted that you should never forget your history.''
Hairston married Margaret Isabel Swanigan in 1939 and became stepfather to her daughter, Jeanne-Marie Swann. In recognition of his contributions to film and television, Hairston received a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame located at 6201 Hollywood Blvd. Hairston died in Los Angles on January 18, 2000 and is interred at Inglewood Park Cemetery in California.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Hairston, Jester, 1901-2000; Deptartment of Music; Spirituals (Songs)--Instrumental settings; Vocal music--United States--20th century; African American history; Arts
- Sound recordings related to Jester Hairston, 1940 -- 1990; 1960 -- 1980; MS040.001; 20.4 Linear Feet; 9 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records that are related to or may be related to Hairston. It includes records of Hairston's work as a composer, a conductor, or choral director; recordings of other musicians performing Hairston's original compositions; and of concerts given in his honor. Records that were inscribed to Hairston and/or his wife Marge, are also located in this series. Records that may be related to Hairston include private recordings or unlabelled records that could be previously unrecorded songs or rehearsal sessions. Foreign language records are located at the end of the series.
  Arrangement
  This series is subdivided into seven groups and arranged alphabetically within each: 1. 12-inch records that are related to Jester Hairston; 2. 12-inch titled and untitled records that may be related to Jester Hairston; and 3. 12-inch record jackets (without records) that are related to Jester Hairston 4. 10-inch records that are related to Jester Hairston; 5. 10-inch titled and untitled records that may be related to Jester Hairston; and 6. 10-inch record jackets (without records) that are related to Jester Hairston 7. 12-inch foreign language records related to Jester Hairston
  Conditions Governing Access
  Physical condition. Open for research.
  - 17th Annual spring music festival, 1980; MS040.001.001.00001; Jefferson High School Music Department (Box 1)
    Open for research.
    Hairston featured as guest conductor./ This date is approximate./ Portland, OR./ Century Custom Recording Service./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
    phonograph record
  - 1965 Stairway of the stars, MS040.001.001.00002; Santa Monica Unified School District (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as guest conductor./ Burbank, California./ Location Recording Service./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1965 Stairway of the stars, MS040.001.001.00003; Santa Monica Unified School District (Box 1)
  - 1967 Pacific music clinic, MS040.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor./ Modesto, CA/ Century Records./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1970 All-state music clinic, MS040.001.001.00005; Kansas State University (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor./ [United States]./ Director Records./ 2 sound discs: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1971 Pops concert: an evening with Jester Hairston, MS040.001.001.00006; Schola Cantorum (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as guest artist./ [United States]./ Custom Fidelity./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1971 South Dakota all-state chorus, MS040.001.001.00007; South Dakota All-State Chorus (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor./ [United States]./ Mark Custom Recording Division./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1972 Virginia music camp: festival of music concert, MS040.001.001.00008; Massanetta Chorus (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor./ Portsmouth, VA./ Virginia Custom Recording Service./ 2 sound discs: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1972 WMEA all-state high school chorus, MS040.001.001.00009; WMEA All-State High School Chorus (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor and artist./ Huntington Station, NY./ Silver Crest Records./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./Originally set of two, one disc missing./
  - 1975 Eastern MENC, MS040.001.001.00010; Howard D. Woodson Senior High School Male Chorus (Box 1)
    Inscribed with Mr. Marvin E. Kelley's address in Iowa./ Huntington Station, NY./ Silver Crest Records./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 1980 Ottawa University Concert Choir, MS040.001.001.00011; Ottawa University Concert Choir (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as artist./ Lawrence, KA./ Audio House High Fidelity./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 30th Annual choral festival: harvest of song, 1971; MS040.001.001.00012; Oklahoma State University (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as conductor and artist./ Oklahoma City, OK./ Century Records./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - 5th Annual concert, 1965; MS040.001.001.00013; Los Cancioueros (Box 1)
    Hairston featured as director and artist./ This date is approximate./ [United States]./ [S.I.]./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./
  - The Afro-American slave song: its African roots and American development, 1978; MS040.001.002.00001; Hairston, Jester (Box 2)
    Hairston featured as artist./ Chapel Hill, NC./ Research Productions./ 2 sound discs: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Ain't that a kick in the head, 1990; MS040.001.002.00002; Hemsley, Sherman (Box 2)
    Inscribed to Hairston by Sherman Hemsley./ New York./ Sutra./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Amen, 1979; MS040.001.002.00004; Fordhamaires (Box 2)
    Hairston featured as artist./ Inscribed to Hairston by Furman Fordham./ This date is approximate./ Mountain View, CA./ Chapel Records ./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Amen!, 1965; MS040.001.002.00005; Staple Singers (Box 2)
    Hairston featured as artist./ [United States]./ Epic ./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Amen!, 1965; MS040.001.002.00006; First Baptist Church of Van Nuys, CA Choir and Chorale (Box 2)
    Hairston featured as artist./ This date is approximate./ Los Angles, CA./ Liberty./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Amen! Amen!, 1982; MS040.001.002.00007; Victor Valley Community College Chorus and College Singers (Box 2)
    Hairston featured as artist, actor, and conductor./ Huntington Station, NY./ Silver Crest Custom./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Two original record jackets included./
  - "And the Angels sing", 1976; MS040.001.002.00008; Chorus of Angels (Box 2)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Elmer L. Davis./ This date is approximate./ Oklahoma City, OK./ Century./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - At the gate of heaven, 1960; MS040.001.002.00009; Terri, Salli (Box 2)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Salli Terri./ This date is approximate./ [United States]./ Capitol./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket, sleeve, and accompanying materials included./
  - The best of Coral Ridge, 1985; MS040.001.003.00001; Coral Ridge Chancel Choir (Box 3)
    Hairston featured as performer./ This date is approximate./ [United States]./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Bill Withers live at Carnegie Hall, 1973; MS040.001.003.00002; Withers, Bill (Box 3)
    Inscribed to unknown person by Bill Withers./ Hollywood, CA./ Sussex./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./ Originally set of two, one disc missing./
  - The blues, 1955; MS040.001.003.00003; Johnny Hodges and his Orchestra (Box 3)
    Marge Hairston's name is inscribed on the cover and her address is on the record label./ This date is approximate./ United States./ Norgran./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - The Branko Krsmanovich Chorus of Yugoslavia at Carnegie Hall, 1965; MS040.001.003.00004; Branko Krsmanovich Chorus (Box 3)
    Inscribed once to Jester Hairston and once to Jester and Marge Hairston by Martin Legat./ This date is approximate./ New York./ Monitor./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket and sleeve included./
  - Calypso Gene on the scene ('72 in review), 1972; MS040.001.003.00005; Farmer, Gene (Box 3)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Gene Farmer./ Hollywood, CA./ Dore./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Camas High School A Capella Choir, 1967 -- 1969; MS040.001.003.00006; Cama High School A Capella Choir (Box 3)
    Hairston featured as artist./ [United States]./ Century./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - The Cathedral Choir of Crenshaw Christian Church, 1960; MS040.001.003.00007; Cathedral Choir of Crenshaw Christian Church (Box 3)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Cleda Mitchell Fleischackes (?)./ This date is approximate./ Glendale, CA./ Whitney./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - The Choraleers of Anaheim, 1980; MS040.001.003.00008; The Choraleers (Box 3)
    Hairston featured as director./ Santa Ana, CA./ Bristol Street Recorders./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - The Choraleers of Anaheim, 1980; MS040.001.003.00009; The Choraleers (Box 3)
  - A Christmas Festival, 1974; MS040.001.003.00010; West Albany High School (Box 3)
    Hairston featured as artist. Also features Jacqueline Hairston./ Burbank, CA./ United Sound./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Christmas with the Beers family, 1966; MS040.001.003.00011; Beers Family (Box 3)
    Hairston featured as artist./ [United States]./ Columbia./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Classic rags and ragtime songs, 1975; MS040.001.003.00012; Anderson, T.J. (Box 3)
    Inscribed to Hairston from T.J. Anderson./ New York./ Smithsonian Collection./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Combined high school choirs, 1980; MS040.001.004.00001; Albany High School (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as director and soloist./ This date is approximate./ Eugene, OR./ Century./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Combined high school choirs, 1980; MS040.001.004.00002; Albany High School (Box 4)
    Physical condition.
  - The concert choir of Ottawa University, 1970; MS040.001.004.00003; Ottawa University Concert Choir (Box 4)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Stanley De Fries./ This date is approximate./ Tulsa, OK./ Arthur C. Sweeny./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - A concert of spirituals with Jester Hairston, 1962; MS040.001.004.00004; Hairston, Jester (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as artist./ Hollywood, CA./ Location Recording Service./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - District 279 Jr. High School, 1977; MS040.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as guest director./ Golden valley, MN./ Mark Custom Recording Division ./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Downey choral music festival, 1968; MS040.001.004.00006; East Junior High School (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as guest conductor./ North Hollywood, CA./ National Custom Recording ./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Eubie Blake featuring Ivan Harold Browning, 1972; MS040.001.004.00007; Blake, Eubie (Box 4)
    Inscribed to Marge and Jester Hairston from Eubie Blake and Ivan Harold Browning ./ Brooklyn, NY./ Eubie Blake Music./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket and sleeve included./
  - Eugene Holmes sings spirituals, 1968; MS040.001.004.00008; Holmes, Eugene (Box 4)
    Inscribed to Hairston from Eugene Holmes./ New York, NY./ Avant Garde./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - An evening of spirituals with Jester Hairston and the Fullerton Jr. College a Capella Choir, 1961; MS040.001.004.00009; Hairston, Jester (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as guest conductor and soloist./ Hollywood, CA./ Location Recording Service./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - An evening of spirituals with Jester Hairston and the Fullerton Jr. College a Capella Choir, 1961; MS040.001.004.00010; Hairston, Jester (Box 4)
  - An evening with Jester Hairston, 1977; MS040.001.004.00011; Carroll County Choral Society (Box 4)
    Hairston featured as artist and soloist./ Reisterstown, MD./ Ster-Art Recording Company./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - Excerpts from Elijah by Felix Mendelssohn, 1972; MS040.001.004.00012; La Jolla Presbyterian Chancel Choir (Box 4)
  - The fire bird - suite/ Symphony of Psalms, 1954; MS040.001.005.00001; L'Orchestre de la Suisse Romande (Box 5)
    Inscribed to Hairston from unknown person./ This date is approximate./ London./ [S.I.]./ 1 sound disc: 33.3 rpm, 12-inch./ Original record jacket included./
  - First annual Archdiocesan high school choral & instrumental festival, 1961; MS040.001.005.00002; Los Angeles Archdiocesan High School Chorus (Box 5)